اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
إِنَّ اللّهَ اصْطَفى آدَمَ وَ نُوحاً وَ آلَ إِبْراهیمَ وَ آلَ عِمْرانَ عَلَى الْعالَمینَ۝
ذُرِّيَّةًۢ بَعْضُهَا مِنۢ بَعْضٍۢ ۗ وَٱللَّهُ سَمِيعٌ عَلِيمٌ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; Allah chose Adam(آدَم), Nuh(نوح), the family of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم), and the family of Imran(عمران) above Al-Alameen(الْعالَمینَ).
Offspring one of the other and Allah is All Hearer, All Knower.
Adam(آدَم) was chosen; Istafa(اصْطَفى);
Istafa(اصْطَفى) means; chose.
So Adam(آدَم) is chosen and Nuh(نوح).
And then, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
آلَ إِبْراهیمَ
And;
آلَ عِمْرانَ
With Adam(آدَم) and Nuh(نوح); Allahسُبحانه وتعالى mentioned their names alone;
Adam(آدَم) and Nuh(نوح).
إِنَّ اللّهَ اصْطَفى آدَمَ وَ نُوحاً
Allah has chosen Adam(آدَم) and Nuh(نوح).
But with Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) and Imran(عمران), Allah said; Aal-Ibrahim(آل-اِبْراهِيْم) and Aal-Imran(آل-عمران).
And Aal(آل) means; the family.
So, Adam(آدَم) was chosen; Nuh(نوح) was chosen, and then, Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) and his family were chosen, and Imran(عمران) and his family were chosen.
ذُرِّيَّةًۢ بَعْضُهَا مِنۢ بَعْضٍۢ ۗ
They are offspring of one another because; Aal-Imran(ال-عمران) are from the descendants of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم),
and Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) is from the descendants of Nuh(نوح), and Nuh(نوح) is from the descendants of Adam(آدَم).
These are the chosen ones of the world.
But then the chosen out of all humanity and all of the creation is; Muhammadﷺ.
Aal-Ibrahim(آل-اِبْراهِيْم) and Aal-Imran(آل-عمران); and Aal-Ibrahim(آل-اِبْراهِيْم) includes the ones who believe in the message of truth.
Because, we know that part of the family of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) are Al-Yahood(اليهود).
But they are not included in this; because as soon as there is Kuffr(كفر), then the ties of relationship are cut.
So they are not part of the Aal-Ibrahim(آل-اِبْراهِيْم) anymore.
And that's why, Ahl al-Bayt(اهل البيت) does not include within them; Abu Lahab(ابو لهب);
Abu Lahab(ابو لهب) is not considered from Ahl al-Bayt(اهل البيت);
Ahl al-Bayt(اهل البيت) of Rasool Allah ﷺ are the ones who believed in Muhammadﷺ from his family.
But the ones who did not believe, they're not included in Ahl al-Bayt(اهل البيت).
And the same thing with Nuh(نوح) when he said; This is my son,
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told him; He's not from your family, he is not part of your relatives to start with.
إِنَّهُۥ عَمَلٌ غَيْرُ صَٰلِحٍۢ ۖ
Because, he's on unrighteous deeds.
Aal-Imran(آل-عمران) are from the descendants of Sayidina Ibrahimعليه السلام.
And Aal-Imran(آل-عمران) are the family of Sayidina Eesaعليه السلام, and that's the family of Zakariyya عليه السلام, and the family of Yahya عليه السلام.
They are from the family the household of Aal-Imran(آل-عمران).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
إِذْ قَالَتِ امْرَأَتُ عِمْرَانَ رَبِّ إِنِّي نَذَرْتُ لَكَ مَا فِي بَطْنِي
This righteous woman; the wife of Imran(عمران); Imran(عمران) is the name of the father.
He's the head of this household; his name is Imran(عمران).
His wife said; Oh Allah! I vowed to you; what is in my womb.
نَذَرْتُ لَكَ مَا فِي بَطْنِي
An-Nazr(نَذَرْ) is a promise and a vow that you give.
Imra'tu Imran(امرأة عمران); she gave a vow; a promise that, what is in a womb(she was pregnant) is for Allah.
Specifically, that means that, this child will serve in the Masjid(مسجد).
Which Masjid(مسجد)?
Al-Masjid al-Aqsa(المسجد الاقصى).
In that time they used to have men, who are devoted to Khidmat ul Masjid(خدمت المسجد).
They were devoted to the serving of the Masjid(مسجد).
The ones, who would fill this job were men.
They didn't allow a women to take this job; it was for men.
And they would live their entire life in the Masjid(مسجد) and serve in the Masjid(مسجد).
So Imra'tu Imran(امرأة عمران) said; Oh Allah! I'm vowing my child to you; to the Khidmah(خدمة) of Al-Masjid(المسجد).
And I think these Ayaat(آيات); that deals with the parents and children; we need to reflect on them.
We're not going to spend a lot of time doing this reflection now.
But take this as a pointer and a tip, when you're reading through the Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an,
when you see the relations between the parents and the children within the righteous families; try to think about it and reflect and contemplate.
Over here, Imra'tu Imran(امرأة عمران) is vowing her child to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to serve in the Masjid(مسجد).
Imra'tu Imran(امرأة عمران); she was not thinking in terms of Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) at all.
She wanted her child to go to the service in the Masjid al-Aqsa(مسجد الاقصى).
Not for a certain time, and then come back to her and generate money; For the whole life.
She wants her son because the service is for men.
She wanted her son to go in the Masjid(مسجد) and serve in the Masjid(مسجد).
I think; we should learn from the ones, whom Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has chosen.
These are the ones whom Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given Istafa(اصْطَفى).
And they should be the role models for us.
We need to take care of the religious matters of our children more than the Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) matters.
Because the one, who is giving them Rizq(رزق) is Allah not us.
We are not the ones, who are giving them Rizq(رزق).
And that's why, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
نَّحْنُ نَرْزُقُهُمْ وَإِيَّاكُمْ ۚ
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
نَحْنُ نَرْزُقُكُمْ وَإِيَّاهُمْ۝
In two Ayaat(آيات).
One Ayah(آية), Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; We give you Rizq(رزق), and We give them Rizq(رزق).
And in another Ayah(آية), Allah says; We give them Rizq(رزق), and We give you Rizq(رزق).
One time; they will mentioned before us, and one time we were mentioned before them.
In all; Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is the One, Who is giving Rizq(رزق).
Allah is the One, Who created every human being, and Allahسُبحانه وتعالى created with the human being its Rizq(رزق).
We are not the ones, who are providing for them.
Therefore, we need to pay attention to the religious matters of our children.
And that's why, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
قُوا أَنفُسَكُمْ وَأَهْلِيكُمْ نَارًا وَقُودُهَا النَّاسُ وَالْحِجَارَةُ
Save yourselves and your families from hell fire. Save yourselves and your families from Hellfire.
Now, He didn't say; save themselves from hunger even though; we should.
So Imra'tu Imran(امرأة عمران) was devoting her child to the serving of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in Al-Masjid al-Aqsa(المسجد الاقصى).
And then, she said;
مُحَرَّرًا
نَذَرْتُ لَكَ مَا فِي بَطْنِي مُحَرَّرًا
Free from all worldly work.
If we just take the word Muharrar(مُحَرَّر), it means; free; freedom.
This word freedom has been used by every revolutionary group in the world.
Everyone is seeking freedom.
Every movement of revolution comes under the banner of freedom.
Freedom is a quality that every human being is striving to get.
And over here, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is giving us the definition of this Istalah(اصطلاح); the definition of this word.
What is freedom?
Because we all want freedom.
So what's the meaning of this word?
What's the definition of freedom?
And we get the definition from the mouth of the wife of Imran(عمران).
When she said that, her child is going to be the servant of Allah, in the Masjid(مسجد) of Allah.
When her son is going into servitude; Abudiyyah(عبوديه); to serve Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
She said; that is Tehreer(تحرير); that is the freedom for my child.
Because if you are not a slave of Allah; you're going to be a slave of something else.
If you're not a servant of Allah; you're going to be serve something else.
If you don't serve Allah; you're going to serve money, you're going to serve your desires, you might serve a king, or a human being.
The only way that you could be free and is when; you devote yourself in sincerity and you serve Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
That's the only way you could be free.
And that's why, Rabie Bin Aamir(ربيع بن عامر); when he went to meet with the Persian commander,
and the Persian commander said; What did you come here for?
Because the Persian commander knows the Arab people before Islam.
The Arab people before Islam were dis-united tribes, hungry, poor; and they were so poor; they would eat the skin of dead animals.
They would eat dead animals; but they would also sometimes eat the skin.
And that was the stereotype that the Persians had; the Persian Empire had about the Arabs of Arabia.
تأکلون جلود الميته
You are so poor that you eat the skin of dead animals.
What are you doing here in the Persian Empire?
This is too advanced for you to come in, what are you doing here?
And then he told him; if you came here because, you need money; I'll give every one of you a certain amount of money.
And then I will give your Ameer(أمير) double.
Go back to your land!
Rabie Bin Aamir(ربيع بن عامر) said;
ابتعثنا الله لنخرج العبادمن عبادة العباد إلى عبادة رب العبادمن عبادة العباد إلى عبادة رب العبادومن ضيق الدنيا إلى سَعَتِ الدُّنيَا وَلآخِرَة
ومن جور الأديان الی سعت الإسلام
He said;
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has sent us, so that we can deliver the creation of Allah, from being slaves of each other, to being the slaves of Allah,
and from the narrowness of this world, to the vastness of this world and the Hereafter,
and from the oppression of other religions to the justice of Islam.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى sent us to free you, from serving each other, to serving Allah.
Because, you are not serving Allah therefore, you're serving each other.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى sent us to free you from this.
So that, you could serve Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and stop serving one another.
And this is the message of Islam; to free the human being; So that the human being can be;
مخلصاً بالله عزّوجل
Pure for Allahسُبحانه وتعالى;
فَتَقَبَّلْ مِنِّىٓ ۖ
Oh Allah! Accept for me;
إِنَّكَ أَنتَ ٱلسَّمِيعُ ٱلْعَلِيمُ۝
Oh Allah! You are verily the All hearer and the All knowerer.
فَلَمَّا وَضَعَتْهَا قَالَتْ رَبِّ إِنِّي وَضَعْتُهَا أُنثَىٰ وَاللَّهُ أَعْلَمُ بِمَا وَضَعَتْ وَلَيْسَ الذَّكَرُ كَالْأُنثَىٰ ۖ
When she delivered her child, she said; Oh my Lord! I have given birth to a female child.
Imra'tu Imran(امرأة عمران); she had a female child.
And females were not traditionally allowed to serve in the Masjid(مسجد); it was only for men.
So she said; Oh Allah! I delivered a female.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَاللَّهُ أَعْلَمُ بِمَا وَضَعَتْ
Allah knows better; what she delivered.
And then, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَلَيْسَ الذَّكَرُ كَالْأُنثَىٰ ۖ
And the male is not like the female.
What does this mean?
وَلَيْسَ الذَّكَرُ كَالْأُنثَىٰ ۖ
Imra'tu Imran(امرأة عمران); she wanted to have a son; a male; so the male could serve in the Masjid(مسجد).
When she was not given a son and was given a daughter; she was upset.
And then, she said; Oh Allahسُبحانه وتعالى! I have delivered a female.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; Allah knows best is what you delivered, and the male is not like the female.
This means that, whatever male you would have delivered; that male will not be better than the female that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given you.
Because the female that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given you is the best of Nisa al-Alameen(نساءلعالمين).
She doesn't know;
اَللَّهُ أَعْلَمُ بِمَا وَضَعَتْ
Allah knows better.
All what she knows; Imra'tu Imran(امرأة عمران); all what she knows is that; she delivered a female. But;
اَللَّهُ أَعْلَمُ بِمَا وَضَعَتْ
Allah knows; who this female is.?
And this female is; Maryamعليها السلام.
اَللَّهُ أَعْلَمُ بِمَا وَضَعَتْ
Allah knows best; what she delivered.
وَلَيْسَ الذَّكَرُ كَالْأُنثَىٰ ۖ
The male will never be like the female.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى Has given you a blessing.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given you the best woman that will ever live on the face of the earth and that is; Sayidatna Maryam(سيدتنا مريم).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
خيرُ نساءِ العالمينَ أربعٌ
The best of the woman of the world are four;
Maryam(مريم) and Asiyah(آسيه) and Khadijah(خديجه) and Fatimah binte Muhammad(فاطمه بنتِ محمدﷺ).
These are the best four.
And the best of them all; was Maryam Binte Imranعليها السلام.
وَاللَّهُ أَعْلَمُ بِمَا وَضَعَتْ وَلَيْسَ الذَّكَرُ كَالْأُنثَىٰ ۖ وَإِنِّي سَمَّيْتُهَا مَرْيَمَ
She named the child Maryam(مريم).
That's the name she chose for the child; Maryam(مريم).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says; every child who is born is stabbed by Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ).
Whenever a child is born, what's the first thing that the child does?
When the child is born?
Cry?
The first thing they do; they cry.
They come out;
یستحل صالحٓا
They come out; crying.
Why do they cry?
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in this Hadith(حديث) is a Muslim that; Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) stabs every child and that's why, the child comes out crying.
And by the way, before continuing the Hadith(حديث); you can see how much Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) hates human beings.
From the moment you're born, he stabs you.
As soon as you come out; he stabs you.
He hates humanity so much.
Subhan Allah(سُبْحان الله)! Who would like to harm, who would want to harm such a lovely child.
But this shows you the evilness and the wickedness of Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ).
And it shows you; how foolish humans are when they follow Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ).
الشَّيْطَانَ لَكُمْ عَدُوٌّ فَاتَّخِذُوهُ عَدُوًّا ۚ
Like Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) and Adam(آدَم) has given us advice.
He said;
If Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) is your enemy, so take him as an enemy.
He's our enemy; from day one he is our enemy, and we should take him as our enemy.
وَكَانَ ٱلشَّيْطَٰنُ لِلْإِنسَٰنِ خَذُولًا۝
he is betraying the son of Adam(آدَم).
This happens to every child.
There is an exception of two.
Who are they?
Who are the who are not stabbed by Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ)?
Maryam(مريم) and Eesa(عيسى).
Maryam(مريم) and Eesa(عيسى) are the only exceptions.
Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) has stabbed every child that was born, with the exception of Maryam(مريم) and Eesa(عيسى); Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) did not stab them.
Why?
Because of the Dua(دُعَا) of the mother of Maryam(مريم).
وَإِنِّي أُعِيذُهَا بِكَ وَذُرِّيَّتَهَا مِنَ الشَّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيمِ۝
And I seek refuge with You Allah, for her and for her offspring from Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ).
So the mother said; Oh Allah! I seek refuge in You to save my child and her offspring from Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ).
So child is Maryam(مريم), and who's the offspring of Maryam(مريم)?
Eesa(عيسى), and its stop right there, there was no other offspring.
So these are the only two, who were excluded from this stabbing of Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says; When he wanted to stab Eesa(عيسى);
زھب یتعن فی الحجاب
Al-Hijab(الحجاب) is the diaphragm; That's Al-Hijab(الحجاب).
So, Eesaعليه السلام and Maryam(مريم) were saved from this stabbing of Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ).
By the way, even though, Christianity claims to be the religion of Eesa(عيسى).
They are missing many of the details of the life of Eesa(عيسى) to start with.
And this is one thing that is missing.
The issue, that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has saved Maryam(مريم) and Eesa(عيسى) in their birth.
And another thing that is missing, and it's one of the best or the most wonderful miracles that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى Has given Sayidina Eesa(سيدنا عيسى) is;
يتكلم في المهد
Speaking at birth.
This is not mentioned in the Bible.
And this is a knowledge that the people who claim to follow Eesa(عيسى), don't even know that Eesa(عيسى) spoke when he was born.
And these are some of the miracles of Eesa(عيسى) that were mentioned in Qur'an.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَتَقَبَّلَهَا رَبُّهَا بِقَبُولٍ حَسَنٍ وَأَنبَتَهَا نَبَاتًا حَسَنًا
So her Lord accepted her with goodly acceptance; He made her grow in a good manner.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is the One, Who is growing up Maryam(مريم) in a Very good way.
And this is a proof and an evidence
that Maryam(مريم) since her birth, until the end of her life, was always righteous, was always taken care of by Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, and was always on the straight path.
This is Sayidatna Maryam(سيدتنا مريم); Mary.
And it's very important to note the fact that throughout her life;
Why? Because the Jews accused Maryam(مريم).
They accused her of Zina(زنا).
They accused her of fornication.
And they do not see Eesa(عيسى) as being a legitimate child.
And they accuse her of sleeping with a carpenter and all of these made up fabricated stories.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is saying the contrary that; Maryam(مريم); Mary, since her birth until the end of her life, was always As-Siddiqah(الصّدّيقه).
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى always called her As-Siddiqah(الصّدّيقه) Qur'an.
As-Siddiqah(الصّدّيقه) is an extreme form of righteousness, or it's a high level of righteousness due to an extreme form Sadaq(صدق); truth.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in many Ayaat(آيات) and Rasool Allah ﷺ in many Ahadith(احاديث) told us about the virtues of Sadaq(صدق); truth.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says that Sadaq(صدق); truth leads to righteousness, and righteousness leads to paradise.
And the man would continue saying the truth until, he is written by Allahسُبحانه وتعالى as being As-Siddique(الصّدّيق).
The more truth you say, and the more truthful you are; the closer you are to the status; the station of Siddique(صدّيق).
And the best or the most prominent type of truth is being truthful with Allah.
There's different forms of truth; truth with the creation, truth with yourself and then, there's truth with Allah.
The highest of all; is the truth with Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
And you are true with your covenant to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
What does that mean?
When you say that you are a Muslim;
truth with Allah means that you are true in that claim, and you fulfill all of the terms of the contract between you and Allah.
Because, we have a contract between us and Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
And that's the highest level of truth.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said about the Sahabah(صحابه) that; They are men;
صَدَقُوا مَا عَاهَدُوا اللَّهَ عَلَيْهِ ۖ
They have been truthful, in their covenant with Allah.
They gave Allah Bay'ah(بيعه).
صَدَقُوا مَا عَاهَدُوا اللَّهَ عَلَيْهِ ۖ
Ahd(عهد) is a contract or Ahd(عهد) is a promise between you and Allah.
Sahabah(صحابه) gave Allah a promise; they have a contract between them and Allah.
And that contract is that; they are going to worship nobody but Allah, and that; they are going to give Nusrah(نصرة); victory to the religion of Allah.
And they have fulfilled the terms of that contract.
So, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says about them; They are men whom fulfilled and have been truthful with Allah.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَأُمُّهُۥ صِدِّيقَةٌ ۖ
When Allah was talking about Sayidina Eesa(سيدنا عيسى); Jesus, Allah said;
And his mother was As-Siddiqah(الصّدّيقة).
So, she have reached this level, and what is the next level above Siddique(صدّيق)?
Nabi(نَبِي); that's the highest, it could get.
And then after that you get into Prophet-hood.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَكَفَّلَهَا زَكَرِيَّا ۖ
She was taken care of by Zakariyya(زَكَرِيا); Zachariah.
Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) says that; Jumhurul-Ulama(جمهُوْرُالْعُلَمَا); the majority of the scholars say that,
Maryam(مريم) is the sister in law of the Zakariyya(زَكَرِيا).
So the wife of Zakariyya(زَكَرِيا); her name is Eeshia(عيشیا) and Maryam(مريم) is her sister.
Some other scholars say that; she's her nice.
Because, they say that Eeshia(عيشیا); actually is the sister of the mother of Maryam(مريم).
So there's a bit of a difference of opinion here, but it's an irrelevant difference of opinion.
But we know that they are relatives.
Zakariyya(زَكَرِيا) is the one, who took care of her.
The way this happened; and just to refresh your memory again that;
Imra'tu Imran(امرأة عمران); the mother of Maryam(مريم), she said;
I'm giving whatever I'm going to deliver to the service of Al-Masjid(المسجد).
The Jews had this law or tradition that,
they would devote some men entirely and completely to take care of Al-Masjid(المسجد) to service the Masjid(مسجد); Al-Masjid Al-Aqsa(المسجد الاقصى).
And this role was for men.
But they accepted Maryam(مريم) even though, she was a woman.
When she was very young, her mother handed her over to the care keepers of Al-Masjid(المسجد),
because she came from this noble and blessed family.
And by the way, the family of Al-Imran(آل-عمران) are the descendants of Dawoodعليه السلام.
Because she is from this blessed family and Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
إِنَّ اللّهَ اصْطَفى آدَمَ وَ نُوحاً وَ آلَ إِبْراهیمَ وَ آلَ عِمْرانَ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
We have chosen Adam(آدَم), and Nuh(نوح), and the family of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم), and the family of Imran(عمران) over all, mankind.
So this is a very blessed family.
Due to the fact that, they are very blessed and noble family among their people; Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); the children of Israel(اسرائيل);
everyone wanted to take care of Maryam(مريم), everyone wanted that honour.
So all of these men, who are the keepers of Al-Masjid al-Aqsa(المسجد الاقصى) are disputing among themselves,
who would have the honour of taking care of Maryam(مريم) to raise her up.
Because, you have to go through training, to take care of the Masjid(مسجد).
So, they were competing and who would get the honour of having Maryam(مريم) so that, they could train her, for the position of being a caretaker of Al-Masjid(المسجد).
They couldn't solve the dispute, so they ended up casting lots.
They used to cast lots.
And by the way, this is something that the nations before use to do.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى Has replaced us with something better, and what does that?
Salatu Istikhara(صلاة استخارا).
The nations before, they didn't know about Salatu Istikhara(صلاة استخارا).
This is something reserved for the ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ.
So they had to cast lots.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
ذَٰلِكَ مِنْ أَنبَاءِ الْغَيْبِ نُوحِيهِ إِلَيْكَ ۚ
وَمَا كُنتَ لَدَيْهِمْ إِذْ يُلْقُونَ أَقْلَامَهُمْ أَيُّهُمْ يَكْفُلُ مَرْيَمَ وَمَا كُنتَ لَدَيْهِمْ إِذْ يَخْتَصِمُونَ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
These are the news of the unseen, you were not with them; when they were casting lots, and who would take care of Maryam(مريم),
and you were not with them; when they were disputing.
So they cast lots, and Allahسُبحانه وتعالى made them, the lots come out on who?
On Zakariyya عليه السلام.
And Zakariyya عليه السلام; is a Nabi(نَبِي) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; and Allah chose him to take care of Maryam عليهِا السلام.
So Zakariyya(زَكَرِيا); he was the sponsor of Maryam(مريم), and he would take care of her, and he would visit her from time to time.
But he used to notice strange things.
He was coming to visit Maryam(مريم) in her place of worship, and he would find with her Rizq(رزق).
Rizq(رزق) is provisions; sustenance from Allah.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in Qur'an mentions it as Rizq(رزق).
It didn't define exactly what it is; but many of the Mufassireen(مفسرين) say
that; she used to get the fruits of summer in winter, and she would get the fruits of winter in summer.
And there's no refrigeration.
And these fruits were fresh.
So it's winter, and she would get fresh summer fruits.
And it's summer, and she would get fresh winter fruits.
It is a miracle.
And in Arabic, there's a difference between Muajiza(معجزة) and Karamah(كرامة).
Muajiza(معجزة) is a miracle that's given to the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء), and Karamah(كرامة) is a miracle that is given to Al-Awliya(الاوليا).
In the case of Maryam(مريم); it's a Karamah(كرامة) that is given to the friends of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
And these are things that were happening frequently.
Because Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; Whenever he would go in and visit her, he would find with her, Rizq(رزق).
So it's not once or twice, it's many times; frequently.
And she's there in the room, and this Rizq(رزق) is coming to her so, Zakariyya عليه السلام asked her;
أَنَّىٰ لَكِ هَٰذَا ۖ
Where is this Rizq(رزق) coming from?
He's wondering; who's bringing you this, I'm the one taking care of you?
And then; this is strange because this fruit; it's impossible to have in Jerusalem in this time of the year.
What was the response of Sayidatna Maryamعليهِ السلام?
She said;
قَالَتْ هُوَ مِنْ عِندِ ٱللَّهِ ۖ
This is from Allah.
And then; she's giving him, this wonderful lesson in Rizq(رزق).
إِنَّ ٱللَّهَ يَرْزُقُ مَن يَشَآءُ بِغَيْرِ حِسَابٍ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى gives the ones, He wants without any limits.
See, what she said; Allah will give you without any limits.
So it's limitless.
The Rizq(رزق) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; there is no limit to it.
We put a lot of effort in pleasing the boss, our children, our friends; we put a lot of effort in pleasing the ones, around us.
And sometimes we do that and we compromise the religion, in the process.
Now for doing that and we're keeping the terms of religion Alhamdulillah(اَلْحَمْدُ لله), that’s Silatur-Rahem(صلةالرحم);
it's fulfilling your rights towards relatives, and towards the friends.
But sometimes we do it and we compromise the religion.
We need to understand and believe firmly, that if you please anyone, while you are upsetting Allahسُبحانه وتعالى;
Allah will make that person or whoever it is; upset with you and Allah will be upset with you.
But if you please Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; Allahسُبحانه وتعالى will make the creation please with you.
And when Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is pleased with you; you won't need anyone else.
See that's the important point.
We're trying to please too many people.
But if we please Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; just pleasing Allah will take care of everything.
And then, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is the only One, Whom, if He's pleased with you, He will give you without limits.
Anything else is within boundaries and limits except with Ridha(رضی) Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
When Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is pleased with you; then Allahسُبحانه وتعالى will show you, the meaning of His name; Al-Kareem(الكريم).
Allah will show you, what the meaning of Al-Kareem(الكريم) is.
And Allah will show you what the meaning of the name Ar-Raheem(الرحيم); the merciful is.
And Allah will show you, what the meaning of His name Ar-Razzaq(الرّزّاق); the Sustainer is.
Allah will show you the meanings of these names of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
And that's why, As-Sahabahرضى الله عنهم and the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and their followers As-Sahabahرضى الله عنهم; they had their goal set.
And that is, to please Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
And they spend their life trying to achieve this goal.
And that's why, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
لَّقَدْ رَضِىَ ٱللَّهُ عَنِ ٱلْمُؤْمِنِينَ إِذْ يُبَايِعُونَكَ تَحْتَ ٱلشَّجَرَة
Allah is pleased with the ones, who gave you the Pledge of Allegiance under the tree.
And these are the one thousand four hundred Sahabah(صحابه), who came and gave the Bay'ah(بيعه) to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said; He's pleased with them.
And that's the ultimate goal that one could achieve; is to please Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Because if you please Allah; Allah will please you.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى will give you without any limits.
When Zakariyya عليه السلام saw this Karamah(كرامة); Miracle, happening to Maryamعليهِ السلام;
he himself desired something from Allah.
See Zakariyya عليه السلام at the time was old,
وَاشْتَعَلَ الرَّأْسُ شَيْبًا
His hair was grey.
And his wife was barren.
She was infertile; She would not give birth; plus she was old.
So it's even complicated further.
And they had no children.
When Zakariyya(زَكَرِيا) saw that, Maryam(مريم) is receiving Rizq(رزق) in a time that is different.
Because, she is getting Rizq(رزق) of summer in winter, and winter in summer.
When he saw that the time is different.
He made a Dua(دُعَا) to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to give him Rizq(رزق) even though, the time is passed.
And the Rizq(رزق), Zakariyya(زَكَرِيا) wanted from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is; a righteous son.
With Maryam(مريم); it was different time, with him; it was past time.
So he decided; he's going to ask Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to give him, this Rizq(رزق).
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى immediately, the following Ayah(آية) after Zakariyya(زَكَرِيا) visited Maryam(مريم) and saw this Rizq(رزق) with her;
the following Ayah(آية) was;
هُنَالِكَ دَعَا زَكَرِيَّا رَبَّهُ ۖ
Then; so when he saw; what is happening to Maryam(مريم); then he made Dua(دُعَا) himself and said;
هُنَالِكَ دَعَا زَكَرِيَّا رَبَّهُ ۖ قَالَ رَبِّ هَبْ لِي مِن لَّدُنكَ ذُرِّيَّةً ةً طَيِّبَةً ۖ إِنَّكَ سَمِيعُ الدُّعَاءِ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
At that time, Zachariya invoked his Lord saying; Oh my Lord! Grant me from You, a good offspring; You are indeed all hearer of invocation.
You hear, what I say.
Zakariyya عليه السلام; notice here, did not say; Oh Allah, give me offspring persay; But he said; righteous.
He said; righteous.
He doesn't just want to have a child; He wants to have a righteous child.
And he made that Dua(دُعَا) to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Immediately, the Dua(دُعَا) was accepted.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَنَادَتْهُ ٱلْمَلَٰٓئِكَةُ وَهُوَ قَآئِمٌ يُصَلِّى فِى ٱلْمِحْرَابِ
The angels called him.
When did they call him?
وَهُوَ قَآئِمٌ يُصَلِّى فِى ٱلْمِحْرَابِ
When he was standing and praying in Al-Mehrab(المحراب); Al-Mehrab(المحراب) is a place of worship.
You, I think would get the meaning from this Ayah(آية);
when Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says that, the angels called him when he was praying;
gives us the impression that, Sayidina Zakariyyahعليه السلام was constantly in a state of Ibadah(عبادة).
Because, how come Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said; when he was standing and praying.
It gives the impression that, Sayidina Zakariyya(سيدنا زَكَرِيا) was in a state Ibadah(عبادة) continuously.
And he received this good news from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى when he was in that Ibadah(عبادة).
And this is interesting to notice, because you could try many things; you could go to the hospital to try solve the problem.
You could go and see a physician.
You could take pills.
You could try your best to solve this problem of infertility.
But the news; Zakariyya(زَكَرِيا) did not receive it, when he was trying, one of these worldly means to solve the problem.
He received the solution of the problem, when he was standing and praying to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
He made the Dua(دُعَا) to Allah, and then he stood and was praying to Allah, and that's when he received the good news.
Even though, the Zakariyya عليه السلام made the Dua(دُعَا) to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, and he entrusted Allah Will except the Dua(دُعَا).
But it was astonishing.
It was astonishing news to him.
Before, we get into the next Ayah(آية), What was the glad tidings that was delivered to Sayidina Zakariyyaعليه السلام?
What did the angels tell him?
They said;
أَنَّ ٱللَّهَ يُبَشِّرُكَ بِيَحْيَىٰ مُصَدِّقًۢا بِكَلِمَةٍۢ مِّنَ ٱللَّهِ وَسَيِّدًا وَحَصُورًا وَنَبِيًّا مِّنَ ٱلصَّٰلِحِينَ۝
Allah is giving you the glad tidings of Yahya(يحيى).
مُصَدِّقًۢا بِكَلِمَةٍۢ مِّنَ ٱللَّهِ
Believing in the word of Allah.
And what's the word of Allah here?
The word of Allah; the word itself is general, but it has a specific meaning here, and that is what?
Who is the word of Allah?
Eesa(عيسى); Eesaعليه السلام is the word of Allah.
كُن فَيَكُونُ۝
He is the word of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
So, Yahya عليه السلام was born before Eesa(عيسى).
Nevertheless, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى saying that, he will believe in Him; believing in the word of Allah.
The word of Allah is Eesaعليه السلام.
Because, he was created by the word of Allah.
He was created by the word of Allah.
Be
And he Became
وَسَيِّدًا
Noble;
وَحَصُورًا
Keeping away from sexual relations with women;
وَنَبِيًّا مِّنَ ٱلصَّٰلِحِينَ۝
A prophet from among the righteous.
These are some of the attributes of Yahya(يحيى).
So he believes in Eesa(عيسى) and he is As-Sayyid(السّيّد);
Sayyid(سيّد) is, noble man; and he is Hasoor(خصور).
Hasoor(خصور); Hasar(خصر) is when you imprison or when you withhold something; that is called Khasar(خصر).
So he was withholding all of his desires; sexual desires.
It implies that he was a very strong man, in terms of controlling these desires, which are natural in the human being.
He had that strong control over these desires.
And as mentioned in the books of Tafseer(تفسير); Yahya عليه السلام never had any relation with woman, because he never got married.
وَنَبِيًّا مِّنَ ٱلصَّٰلِحِينَ۝
And a prophet from among the righteous.
Zakariyya عليه السلام; when he received this astonishing news, he asked the question; he said;
قَالَ رَبِّ أَنَّىٰ يَكُونُ لِى غُلَٰمٌ وَقَدْ بَلَغَنِىَ ٱلْكِبَرُ وَٱمْرَأَتِى عَاقِرٌ ۖ
He said; Oh my Lord! How can I have a son, when I'm very old, and my wife is barren?
His wife is barren.
So she never had children and he's very old at that time.
So he's wondering; how could this happen?
The answer was given to him.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
قَالَ كَذَٰلِكَ ٱللَّهُ يَفْعَلُ مَا يَشَآءُ۝
Thus Allah does what He wills.
And if we think about it deeply; we would find that the creation of Yahya عليه السلام is not more astonishing than our creation.
The only thing is that we got used to a certain way of reproduction.
But Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is the One, Who made the law this way, and Allahسُبحانه وتعالى can change it.
So, this is the answer that Sayidina Zakariyya(سيدنا زَكَرِيا) received.
Sayidina Zakariyya(سيدنا زَكَرِيا) wanted the sign from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى that will indicate to him that his wife is pregnant.
He said; he wants an Ayah(آية), Ayah(آية) mean; sign.
قَالَ رَبِّ ٱجْعَل لِّىٓ ءَايَةً ۚ
Oh Allah! Give me a sign.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
قَالَ آيَتُكَ أَلَّا تُكَلِّمَ النَّاسَ ثَلَاثَةَ أَيَّامٍ إِلَّا رَمْزًا ۗ
He said; Oh my Lord! Make a sign for me.
Allah said; Your sign is that, you shall not speak to mankind for three days, except with signals.
The meaning of the sign is that; Sayidina Zakariyyahعليه السلام would not be able to speak except Dhikr(ذكر).
And this phase would continue for three days.
So he speaks fine.
And then, suddenly for three days; he lost the ability to speak.
And he was only able to make Dhikr(ذكر) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
So, how can he communicate with people?
He communicate with them by; signs.
He would make signs.
إِلَّا رَمْزًا ۗ
Except through signs.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told him during these three days;
وَاذْكُر رَّبَّكَ كَثِيرًا وَسَبِّحْ بِالْعَشِيِّ وَالْإِبْكَارِ۝
And remember your Lord much, and glorify Him in the afternoon and in the morning.
And these are the time of Adhkaar(اذكار).
When do we make the Dhikr(ذكر) of As-Sabah(الصباح)?
We make it after Fajr(فجر).
And when do we make the Dhikr(ذكر) of nighttime?
We do it after Asr(عصر).
And this is in this Ayah(آية).
وَاذْكُر رَّبَّكَ كَثِيرًا وَسَبِّحْ بِالْعَشِيِّ وَالْإِبْكَارِ۝
Remember the name of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in the morning and afternoon.
These were the Ayaat(آيات) from Surat(سورت) Al-Imran(آلعمران).
Let's read the Ayaat(آيات) which are talking about the same story from Surat(سورت) Maryam(مريم).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
ذِكْرُ رَحْمَتِ رَبِّكَ عَبْدَهُ زَكَرِيَّا۝
إِذْ نَادَىٰ رَبَّهُ نِدَاءً خَفِيًّا۝
قَالَ رَبِّ إِنِّي وَهَنَ الْعَظْمُ مِنِّي وَاشْتَعَلَ الرَّأْسُ شَيْبًا وَلَمْ أَكُن بِدُعَائِكَ رَبِّ شَقِيًّا۝
وَإِنِّي خِفْتُ الْمَوَالِيَ مِن وَرَائِي وَكَانَتِ امْرَأَتِي عَاقِرًا فَهَبْ
فَهَبْ لِي مِن لَّدُنكَ وَلِيًّا۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعال says about Sayidina Zakariyya(سيدنا زَكَرِيا).
He said;
My Lord! Indeed my bones have grown feeble.
He's very old.
And gray hair has spread on my head, and I have never been unblessed in my invocation to you.
He said; Oh Allah! You always respond to my Dua(دُعَا).
Zakariyya(زَكَرِيا) said;
وَإِنِّي خِفْتُ الْمَوَالِيَ مِن وَرَائِي
I verily fear my relatives after me.
Zakariyya عليه السلام being the Nabi(نَبِي); he was the one responsible for the religious affairs of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
Sayidina Zakariyya(سيدنا زَكَرِيا), when he became old; he was worried that there's no one qualified to take over after him.
Therefore, he wanted to have a child that would be strong and capable to lead Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل),
and to teach them, and to bring them back to the straight path.
So he said;
فَهَبْ لِي مِن لَّدُنكَ وَلِيًّا۝
So give me from Yourself a heir.
يَرِثُنِي وَيَرِثُ مِنْ آلِ يَعْقُوبَ ۖ وَاجْعَلْهُ رَبِّ رَضِيًّا۝
Who shall inherit me and inherit the property of Yaqoob(يعقوب).
What inheritance are we talking about here?
What is the inheritance?
It is Prophet-hood.
It is not wealth.
Because Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
إنَّا مَعَاشِرَالْأَنْبِيَاءِ لَا نُورَثُ
We; the prophets; we do not leave behind an inheritance.
مَا تَرَكْنَاهُ صَدَقَة
Whatever we leave behind is As-Sadaqah(الصّدقه); charity.
So, here Zakariyya(زَكَرِيا) wants to inherit to his son, Prophet-hood.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said; Oh Zakariyya(زَكَرِيا)! Verily, We give you the glad tidings of a son.
اسْمُهُ يَحْيَىٰ لَمْ نَجْعَل لَّهُ مِن قَبْلُ سَمِيًّا۝
Here, we have another attribute of Yahya(يحيى).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; We have given that name to none before him.
His name is Yahya(يحيى); the first person to be named Yahya(يحيى) in the whole history of the world, was Sayidina Yahyaعليه السلام.
This was a new name that was chosen for Sayidina Yahyaعليه السلام before he was delivered.
And this name was given to him by Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
The name; Yahya(يحيى) was not chosen by the Zakariyya(زَكَرِيا) or his wife.
The name Yahya(يحيى) was chosen by Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Allah is the one who named him Yahya(يحيى).
And he asked the same question; how can this happen when I'm old and my wife is barren?
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says here;
قَالَ كَذَٰلِكَ قَالَ رَبُّكَ هُوَ عَلَيَّ هَيِّنٌ وَقَدْ خَلَقْتُكَ مِن قَبْلُ وَلَمْ تَكُ شَيْئًا۝
He said; Your Lord says; it is easy for me.
Certainly, I have created you before, when you have been nothing.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said; it's easy for me to create Yahya(يحيى) this way.
You were nothing before.
Just like, you were nothing; it's easy to create Yahya عليه السلام.
Now, the following Ayaat(آيات), or actually, this Ayah(آية) is also similar to the Ayah(آية) of Al-Imran(آلعمران) in terms of his inability to speak.
But what is different here; is that even though, he was unable to speak; he never stopped calling the people to making;
الأمر بالمعروف والنهي عن المنكر
Zakariyya(زَكَرِيا); even though, he was unable to speak for those three days; he did not discontinue in joining good and forbidding evil.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَخَرَجَ عَلَىٰ قَوْمِهِۦ مِنَ ٱلْمِحْرَابِ فَأَوْحَىٰٓ إِلَيْهِمْ أَن سَبِّحُواْ بُكْرَةً وَعَشِيًّا۝
Then, he came out to his people from his place of worship, and he told them by signs, to glorify Allah in the morning and in the afternoons.
So even though, he was unable to speak; he still was giving the people orders using signs, that they should make the Dhikr(ذكر) to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
And this is an indication to us that we are in our full physical abilities, and we are withholding;
أمر بالمعروف والنهي عن المنكر
We are withholding Da'wah(دعوة); even though, we are fully capable of doing it.
Sayidina Zakariyyahعليه السلام was not capable of speaking for three days, that did not deter him from fulfilling his duties of Da'wah(دعوة) to his people.
And this shows you the amazing devotion, that the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى had.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in the next three Ayaat(آيات); actually four; talks about Sayidina Yahya(سيدنا يحيى).
Allah says;
يَا يَحْيَىٰ خُذِ الْكِتَابَ بِقُوَّةٍ ۖ
Allah says; Oh Yahya(يحيى)! Hold fast the scripture.
خُذِ الْكِتَابَ
Kitab(كتاب) is a scripture; At-Torah(التّوراة).
بِقُوَّةٍ ۖ
What does this word mean; Quwwah(قُوَّة)?
Here it says; hold fast.
But what is the meaning of the word Quwwah(قُوَّة)?
Quwwah(قُوَّة) is power and strength.
That's the meaning of Quwwah(قُوَّة).
What this means is that; you hold fast to all of the commands of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, and you don't let go of them.
So you never give up and you never buckle down.
You're always holding fast, holding strong to the commands of Allah.
Yahya عليه السلام; because we need to understand the position of Yahya(يحيى).
Yahya عليه السلام is young and he is going to be the Nabi(نَبِي) of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) who, went corrupt, and went astray.
And this young man will be responsible for this ummah(امة); for this nation.
Therefore; he must have that strength and confidence and power.
Otherwise, he would not be able to function.
And he would be swept away by the ocean of corruption that was existing in the time.
Sayidina Yahyaعليه السلام never gave up this order of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى,
and the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; they never give up the orders of Allah; they fulfill them.
So, Sayidina Yahya(سيدنا يحيى) received this order from Allah.
And that is that you should hold fast and strong to the religion.
So Sayidina Yahyaعليه السلام held strong to the religion of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى,
and he ended up giving his life for the religion of Allah, and he died as As-Shaheed(الشَّهِيد).
Because, of holding strong to the religion; Sayidina Yahyaعليه السلام was assassinated.
That was the end of the life of Sayidina Yahya(سيدنا يحيى).
It was a life of struggle; a life of striving; a difficult life.
But Sayidina Yahya(سيدنا يحيى) was able to hold throughout that period with patience, until he faced Allahسُبحانه وتعالى as As-Shaheed(الشَّهِيد).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; now even though; Allah Has given him this very strong responsibility, or very heavy responsibility,
but Allahسُبحانه وتعالى gave him the tools and the ability to fulfill it.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَآتَيْنَاهُ الْحُكْمَ صَبِيًّا۝
We Have given him the judgment, and the understanding, and the wisdom; when he was young.
Because Allahسُبحانه وتعالى does not overburden a person.
Allah will not ask you to do something, you're un capable of doing.
Since, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has put a very heavy responsibility on Sayidina Yahya(سيدنا يحيى).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى also equipped Sayidina Yahya(سيدنا يحيى) with the tools to carry on with that responsibility and that is;
الْحُكْمَ صَبِيًّا
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى Has given him this understanding very, very early on.
And the Mufassireen(مفسرين) mentions some things, for example;
they say that Yahya(يحيى) was a kid, was a child and the children came to him and said;
Let's go and play; very young child.
So Sayidina Yahyaعليه السلام said;
ما لله بخلقنا
We were not created to play.
So he was serious from his childhood.
وَحَنَانًا مِّن لَّدُنَّا
He was sympathetic.
Don't understand that strength means; I mean; because sometimes, we misinterpret words.
Don't think that strength means; being extreme, or being rude, or being rough.
That's not the meaning of the word strong.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was the strongest.
But he was still the most merciful.
بِالْمُؤْمِنِينَ رَءُوفٌ رَّحِيمٌ۝
With the believers; merciful and compassionate.
Because sometimes, we think that strong means that, you have a very rough heart, insensitive, have no sympathy, no mercy that's not what is meant by strength.
What is meant by strength is; that you're holding to the commands of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى completely.
All of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allah was sympathetic, but Sayidina Yahya(سيدنا يحيى); that was a strong attribute of him.
Some of the Mufassireen(مفسرين) say; it means; sympathetic towards his parents.
Some of them say; its general; he was sympathetic towards all people.
وَزَكَوٰةً ۖ
And he was pure.
وَكَانَ تَقِيًّا۝
And he was righteous.
وَبَرًّا بِوَالِدَيْهِ وَلَمْ يَكُن جَبَّارًا عَصِيًّا۝
And dutiful towards his parents, and he was neither arrogant nor disobedient.
Security and peace is important for us in our life.
The most difficult phases are the transition phases that we go through.
And we go through three transition phases.
When we're in the wombs of our mothers; we spend nine months in the comfort and warmth of the mother's body.
It's very cozy and small room warm.
So the child is comfortable; you never hear the child crying in the womb of the mother.
When the child is delivered; the child is going through a completely different stage of their life.
They're going from the nine months stage in the womb to a completely different world.
So the warmth and small, coziness of the womb of the mother disappears.
Suddenly, you come in a completely open space.
So the first reaction of the child is what?
Cry.
It's a difficult transition.
That phase of transition is difficult.
Because you're going to an entirely different stage.
You're going to the unexpected and the unknown.
And then; we live in this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) and we get used to it.
Unfortunately, some of us get too much attached to it.
We spent here some time and then it's time for us to move to the next stage.
So we go through another transition phase, and that is; death.
ان سكرات الموت
The last moments, you find that the person is going through consciousness and unconsciousness, and that alternates.
That person is actually going back and forth, in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا); in and out.
And that transition phase, is slowly taking the person out of the realm of this world.
Slowly, slowly, he's leaving this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) and the person is aware that he's leaving.
And that's much much more difficult than the transition phase that we talked about before.
Because you spent a long time in this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), and now you're leaving to a completely unknown world and that is, Al-Barzakh(البرزخ); the grave.
And those are very difficult moments.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ has spoken them in the Ahadith(احاديث) and the Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an;
وَجَاءَتْ سَكْرَةُ الْمَوْتِ بِالْحَقِّ ۖ ذَٰلِكَ مَا كُنتَ مِنْهُ تَحِيدُ۝
Now the moments of death have approached you; that is what you're trying to run away from.
You can't run away from it now; you're facing it.
And here you are; you're going to cross the line.
And as soon as you cross it; there's no way back.
That's another very critical and difficult phase of the human being.
And then you are living in your graves; you have awareness.
Even though, your body can't move, but you're still conscious.
And now it's time for you to go through the third transition phase.
And that is; the resurrection and this is the worse.
Because now; you suddenly have a grave that has popped open; you crawl out of that grave.
And you come and see an entirely different world.
The sky above your head is cracking.
The stars are falling down.
The moon knocked out of his orbit.
The sun right over your head.
Mountains are exploding and turning into dirt.
The oceans are catching fire and burning.
There's an earthquake and it's cracking open.
And you see people running around you as if they're drunk.
So that is the worst; that is the worst of the three transition stages.
And this is when we need security and peace most.
Because these are the most difficult moments.
When you read the description of what happens in Al-Ba'th(اَلْبَعَثْ); it is something unbelievable.
If we are able to comprehend it.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has give Sayidina Yahya(سيدنا يحيى) very, very interesting blessing.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَسَلَامٌ عَلَيْهِ يَوْمَ وُلِدَ وَيَوْمَ يَمُوتُ وَيَوْمَ يُبْعَثُ حَيًّا۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; And peace be on him; the day he was born; and the day he dies; and the day he will be raised up again.
See in these three difficult moments; these critical moments; when you are in great need, in dire need of peace;
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given that peace to Sayidina Yahya(سيدنا يحيى).
Allah has given him peace when he was born; the day he was born.
And Allah gave him peace; the day he died.
And Allah Will give him peace the day he will be resurrected again.
We ask Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to give us peace.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ